<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-ietf-bier-ipv6-requirements-06"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="BIER IPv6 Requirements">BIER IPv6 Requirements</title>

    <author fullname="Mike McBride" initials="M" surname="McBride">
      <organization>Futurewei</organization>

      <address>
        <email>michael.mcbride@futurewei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Jingrong Xie" initials="J" surname="Xie">
      <organization>Huawei</organization>

      <address>
        <email>xiejingrong@huawei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Senthil Dhanaraj" initials="S" surname="Dhanaraj">
      <organization>Huawei</organization>

      <address>
        <email>senthil.dhanaraj@huawei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Rajiv Asati" initials="R" surname="Asati">
      <organization>Cisco</organization>

      <address>
        <email>rajiva@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    
       <author fullname="Yongqing Zhu" initials="Y" surname="Zhu">
      <organization>China Telecom</organization>

      <address>
        <email>zhuyq8@chinatelecom.cn</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    
    <author initials="G." surname="Mishra" fullname="Gyan S. Mishra">
      <organization>
Verizon Inc.
      </organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>
            13101 Columbia Pike
          </street>
          <city>
            Silver Spring
          </city>
          <region>
          </region>
          <code>
            MD 20904
          </code>
          <country>
            United States of America
          </country>
        </postal>
        <phone>
          301 502-1347
        </phone>
        <email>
          gyan.s.mishra@verizon.com
        </email>
      </address>
    </author>

        <author fullname="Jeffrey Zhang" initials="J" surname="Zhang">
      <organization>Juniper</organization>

      <address>
        <email>zzhang@juniper.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="11" month="August" year="2020"/>

    <abstract>
      <t>There have been several proposed solutions with BIER being used in IPv6. But there
      hasn't been a document which describes the problem and lists the requirements. 
      The goal of this document is to describe the BIER IPv6
      requirements, summarize the encapsulation modes of the proposed solutions, guide the working group in
      understanding the benefits and drawbacks of the various solutions, and
      help in the development of acceptable solutions.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>Bit Index Explicit Replication (BIER) <xref target="RFC8279"/> is an
      architecture that provides optimal multicast forwarding, without
      requiring intermediate routers to maintain per-flow state, through the
      use of a multicast-specific BIER header. <xref target="RFC8296"/>
      defines two types of BIER encapsulation to run on physical links: one is
      BIER MPLS encapsulation to run on various physical links that support
      MPLS, the other is non-MPLS BIER Ethernet encapsulation to run on
      ethernet links, with an ethertype 0xAB37. This document describes using
      BIER in non-MPLS IPv6 environments. We explain the requirements of
      transporting IPv4/IPv6 multicast payloads through an IPv6 network 
      using BIER. This may include IPv6 encapsulation and generic IPv6 tunnelling. 
      The goal of this document is to help the BIER WG evaluate the BIER v6 
      requirements and solutions in order to begin adopting solution drafts.</t>

      <section anchor="requirements-language" title="Requirements Language">
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
        "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
        document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
        target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="terminology" title="Terminology">
        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>BIER: Bit Index Explicit Replication. Provides optimal
            multicast forwarding through adding a BIER header and removing
            state in intermediate routers.</t>

            <t>BUM: Broadcast, Unknown Unicast, Multicast. Term used to
            describe the three types of Ethernet modes that will be forwarded
            to multiple destinations</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Problem Statement">
      
      <t>The problem is the ability of the network to transport BUM packets, with BIER headers, in an IPv6 environment. 
      In many IPv6 network deployments, non-MPLS encapsulation is used for unicast as the data-plane. It is likewise 
      expected to have BIER IPv6 deployments which depend on these same unicast technologies for incremental deployment
      including traversing through non-BFR routers.</t>
      
      <t>Below is a simple scenario that needs BIER IPv6 encapsulation and forwarding:</t>

      <t><figure align="center">
          <artwork><![CDATA[      
      +--------------------------------------------+
      |                                            |
      |                                         +------+
      |                                         | BFER |
  +------+       +-------+       +-----+        +------+
  | BFIR |       |Non-BFR|       | BFR |           |
  +------+       +-------+       +-----+        +------+
      |                                         | BFER |
      |                IPv6 Network             +------+
      +--------------------------------------------+
      ]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>

      <t>This scenario depicts the need to replicate bier packets from a
      BFIR to BFERs across an IPv6 core. The IPv6 environment may include a
      variety of link types, may be entirely IPv6, may be dual stack or any
      type of combination which includes IPv6. Regardless of the environment,
      there are times when a BIER header, including the BIER BitString used to
      determine the set of BIER forwarding egress routers, will need to
      traverse a IPv6 domain. The ways in which BIER will function in an IPv6
      environment is the problem that needs to be solved. </t>
      
    </section>

    <section title="Conceptual Models For BIER IPv6 Encapsulation and Forwarding">
    <t>This analysis introduces two conceptual models for BIER IPv6 
     encapsulation and forwarding based on the experience and examples that 
     have been seen in the IETF community. </t>
    
      <section title="Transport-Independent Model">
      <t>The first conceptual model is a Transport-Independent Model that views IP tunnels
      as links of BIER, and views BIER as an independent "Layer-2.5". </t>
      <t><figure align="left">
          <artwork><![CDATA[      
      |<----------(L2.5 BIER(P2MP) Tunnel)-------->|
      |                                            |
      |    +~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~+          +~~~~+    |
      |   /                    \        /      \   |  
  +------+       +-------+       +-----+        +------+
  | BFIR |-------|Non-BFR|-------| BFR |--------| BFER |
  +------+       +-------+       +-----+        +------+

  ------- physical link 
    
  ~~~~~~~ IPv6(P2P) tunnel
  
  <-----> BIER(P2MP) tunnel
      ]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>
        <t>In this model, an IPv6 tunnel works as a link-layer of BIER, and BIER 
        works as a transport-independent layer (or layer-2.5) over a virtual-link (IPv6 tunnel).
        On each BFR, the IPv6 tunnel of the receiving packet is decapsulated, 
        and a new IPv6 tunnel is encapsulated before sending the packet to the next-hop BFR neighbour.
        </t>
        
        <t>From the view of the IPv6 layer, the BIER header is a kind of Upper-layer header (Layer-4).
         From the view of the BIER layer, the IPv6 encapsulation is a tunnel working as a "link" of BIER.
         With an End-to-End view, the tunnel from BFIR to BFERs is a Layer-2.5 BIER (P2MP) tunnel, and the 
         BFIR-id is the BIER packet source-origin identifier, and is unchanged through the BIER domain from BFIR to BFERs.</t>
         
         <t>This model is similar to the "MPLS over IP" <xref target="RFC4023"/> or "MPLS over UDP" <xref target="RFC7510"/> approach.
         A more general output of such approach in IETF is "MPLS Segment Routing over IP" <xref target="RFC8663"/>. 
         It makes use of IPv4/IPv6 tunnel, IPv4/IPv6 UDP tunnel and IPv4/IPv6 GRE tunnel to encapsulate the MPLS-based instructions.
         In fact, BIER-MPLS could use this approach directly since BIER-MPLS is based on MPLS. </t>
         
         <t>There may be, however, in certain cases some difficulty with allocation of an MPLS label 
         and advertisement through the control-plane.
         For example, a simple inter-AS BIER deployment may want to use the 
         auto-configuration of BIFT-id using Non-MPLS BIER encapsulation 
         [RFC8296] as illustrated in <xref target="I-D.geng-bier-ipv6-inter-domain"/>.
         This brings the need of a new "Next Header" value to indicate the "Non-MPLS" BIER header. </t>
         
         <t>For IPv4/IPv6 GRE, the "Next Header" is the 16-bit "Protocol Type" field, and has adequate space for such requirement.</t>
         <t>For IPv4/IPv6 UDP, the "Next Header" is the 16-bit "Destination Port" field, and has adequate space for such requirement.</t>
         <t>For IPv4/IPv6, the "Next Header" is a 8-bit value and needs to be allocated from the "Assigned Internet Protocol Numbers" registry.</t>
         
        <t>Reassembly/Re-fragmentation of a packet has to be executed on each BFR in such case.
        This may be common and even friendly for a protocol stack in a BFR software implementation, but 
        it may impose cost for a BFR hardware implementation. </t>
        <t>IPv6 functions that are expected to be executed from BFIR to BFER are assumed to be broken 
        on the BFRs, for example, IPv6 Fragmentation/Assembly or IPSEC ESP. 
        This is because the "IPv6 tunnel" and all its functions is "terminated" on the BFRs.
        These functions, if desired, may need to be re-designed in the "Layer-2.5" BIER mode.</t>
        
        <t>For deployment security, it is necessary to ensure the "BIER" packet is only using the allowed IPv6 tunnel.</t>
        
      </section>
      
      <section title="IPv6-Integrated Model">
      <t>The second conceptual model is an IPv6-Integrated Model that integrates BIER as part of the IPv6 data plane, 
      making it a "Layer-3 BIER" approach.</t>
      <t><figure align="left">
          <artwork><![CDATA[      
       |<----------(L3 BIER(P2MP) tunnel)--------->|
       |                                           |
  +------+       +-------+       +-----+        +------+
  | BFIR |-------|Non-BFR|-------| BFR |--------| BFER |
  +------+       +-------+       +-----+        +------+
  
  ------- physical link 
  
  <-----> BIER(P2MP) tunnel
      ]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>
        <t>In this model, BIER works as part of the IPv6 data plane. 
        BFIR and BFERs work as IPv6 (P2MP) tunnel endpoints, and BFRs 
        work as IPv6 segment endpoints. On each BFR, the segment endpoint 
        behaviour of IPv6 data plane is executed, and there is no decapsulation 
        of receiving IPv6 tunnel and encapsulation of new IPv6 tunnel for sending. </t>
        
        <t>In this mode, the BIER header is integrated into the IPv6 extension header and processing of 
         the BIER header (e.g., the BitString) is implemented as part of the IPv6 extension header processing. 
         The IPv6 source address is the BIER packet source-origin identifier, and is unchanged through the 
         BIER domain from BFIR to BFERs. </t>
         
         <t>This model is similar to many examples emerging in the IETF community which soley use the IPv6 data plane.
         SRv6 introduced in <xref target="RFC8754"/> and <xref target="I-D.ietf-spring-srv6-network-programming"/> is an example.
         The benefits of such approach includes reducing the number of encapsulation layers,
         capability of deployment with non-capable routers in a network, 
         extending the technology in a wider inter-AS scope using IP reachability,
         and capability of integrating the functions of the IPv6 data plane.</t>
         
         <t>This model typically needs an extension to IPv6 data plane, with an IPv6 extension header or Option introduced. </t>
         <t>IPv6 functions that are expected to be executed from BFIR to BFER is 
         supported if correctly designed, for example, IPv6 Fragmentation/Assembly or IPSEC ESP.</t>
         <t>For deployment security, it is necessary to ensure the "BIER" packet is in a trusted IPv6-based domain.</t>
      </section>
      
     <section title="Encapsulation Approaches Considered">
      <t> A number of approaches to the design of BIER-IPv6 encapsulation were
      investigated by the BIER Working Group and were discussed in IETF
      meetings and on the BIER list.  This section divides these approaches 
      into the two conceptual models.</t>
       
     <t>Transport-Independent Model approaches include: </t>
       <t><list style="">
       <t>Transport-Independent BIER <xref target="I-D.xu-bier-encapsulation"/>.</t>
       <t>BIERin6 <xref target="I-D.zhang-bier-bierin6"/>.</t>
       </list></t>
     <t></t>
     <t>IPv6-Integrated Model approaches include: </t>
       <t><list style="">
       <t>BIER-over-IPv6 <xref target="I-D.pfister-bier-over-ipv6"/>.</t>
       <t>BIERv6 <xref target="I-D.xie-bier-ipv6-encapsulation"/>.</t>
       </list></t>       
     </section>
     
    </section>

    <section title="Requirements">
      <t>There have been several suggested requirements, on the BIER email
      list and in meetings, which have been used to form BIER IPv6 requirements 
      used to help the wg evaluate against the proposed solutions. 
      There is also many further discussions on the list about BIER IPv6 
      requirements from different scenarios. </t>
      
      <t>Considering that the importance of requirement for BIER IPv6 solution is 
      different, in this document, the requirements are divided into two groups: 
      mandatory and optional. The requirements in the mandatory group are considered 
      necessary for any BIER IPv6 solution, while the requirements in the optional 
      group should be considered but are not mandatory. </t>
      
    <section title="Mandatory Requirements">  

      <section title="L2 Agnostic">
        <t>The solution must be agnostic to the underlying L2 data link type.</t>
      </section>
      
      <section title="Support BIER architecture">
        <t>The solution must support the BIER architecture. </t>

        <t>Multiple sub-domains bound to one or many topologies or algorithms,
        multiple sets for more BFERs, multiple Bit String Lengths for different forwarding capabilities, and 
        multiple BIFTs for ECMP are considered essential functions of BIER and need to be supported.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Conform to existing IPv6 Spec">
      <t>The proposed encapsulation must conform to the IPv6 specification and 
          guidelines as described in RFC8200. If new extensions to existing
          IPv6 specification are required, it needs to be discussed and 
          reviewed by the 6man working-group.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Support deployment with Non-BFR routers">
        <t>The solution must support deployments with Non-BFR routers.
        This is beneficial to the deployment of BIER, especially 
        in early deployments when some routers do not support 
        BIER forwarding but support IPv6 forwarding. This is also the 
        No.1 charter item, "Transition Mechanisms and Partial Deployments" of the BIER WG.</t>
      </section>
      
      <section title="Support Deployment Security">
      <t>The proposed solution must include careful security considerations, 
      including all that is already considered in BIER architecture RFC8279 and RFC8296, 
      and other security concerns that may raise due to the addition of IPv6. </t>
      </section>
      
      <section title="Support OAM">
      <t>BIER OAM MAY be supported, either directly using existing method, or specify some variant method for the same function.
      It may be considered essential as part of the BIER architecture in some cases. </t>
      </section>
      
      </section>
      
    <section title="Recommended Requirements">
    
      
      <section title="Support IPSEC">
      <t>IPSEC is optional to IPv6 and multicast. It is preferred to support IPSEC, including AH/ESP. 
      If IPSEC is to be supported, it shouldn't require hop-by-hop encryption/decryption.</t>
      </section>
      
      <section title="Support Fragmentation">
      <t>As part of IPv6 specification [RFC8200], BIER IPv6 may support fragmentation on BFIR and assembly on BFER. 
      Support of Fragmentation can enhance the capability of BIER leveraging the BIER-MTU as introduced in section 3 of [RFC8296].
      If Fragmentation is to be supported, it shouldn't require fragmentation and re-assembly at each hop.</t>
      </section>
      
      <section title="Support hardware fast path">
        <t>If a proposed solution is intended for some scenarios like service-provider networks, it should enable the 
        processing and forwarding of BIER packets in hardware fast path.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>Some BIERv6 encapsulation proposals do not require any action from
      IANA while other proposals require new BIER Destination Option
      codepoints from IPv6 sub-registries, new "Next header" values, or
      require new IP Protocol codes. This document, however, does not require
      anything from IANA.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t/>
      <t>There are no security issues introduced by this draft.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgement">
      <t/>

      <t>Thank you to Eric Rosen for his listed set of requirements on the
      bier wg list.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8279'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8296'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2473'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8200'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6513'?>
      
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.1112'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4023'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.7510'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8663'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8754'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.pfister-bier-over-ipv6'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.xu-bier-encapsulation'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.zhang-bier-bierin6'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.xie-bier-ipv6-encapsulation'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.geng-bier-ipv6-inter-domain'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-spring-srv6-network-programming'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-bier-use-cases'?>
    </references>
 
    <section title="Solutions Evaluation">
      <t>The following are solutions that have been proposed to solve BIER in
      IPv6 environments. Some solutions propose encoding while others propose
      encapsulation. It is recommended for the wg to evaluate these solutions against
      the requirements listed previously in order to make informed decisions on solution 
      readiness.</t>

      <t>As illustrated in these examples, the BIER header, or the BitString,
      may appear in the IPv6 Header, IPv6 Extension Header, IPv6 Payload, or
      IPv6 Tunnel Packet:</t>

      <section title="BIER-ETH encapsulation in IPv6 networks">
        <t><figure>
            <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
      +---------------+-----------------+-------------------
      |   Ethernet    |   BIER header   | payload
      |  (ethType =   | (BIFT-id, ...)  |
      |    0xAB37)    |                 |
      |               |  Next Header    |
      +---------------+-----------------+-------------------
          ]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>

        <t>BIER-ETH encapsulation (BIER header for Non-MPLS networks as
        defined in <xref target="RFC8296"/>) can be used to transport the
        multicast data in the IPv6 network by encapsulating the multicast user
        data payload within the BIER-ETH header. </t>
		<t>Mixed use of BIER-ETH in a IPv6 solution is up to the solution 
		and is outside the scope of this document.</t>

        <t/>
      </section>

      <section title="Encode Bitstring in IPv6 destination address">
        <t><figure>
            <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
   +---------------+-------------------
   |  IPv6 header  | payload
   | (BitString in |
   | DA lower bits)|
   |  Next Header  |
   +---------------+-------------------
          ]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>

        <t>As described in <xref target="I-D.pfister-bier-over-ipv6"/>, The
        information required by BIER is stored in the destination IPv6
        address. The BIER BitString is encoded in the low-order bits of the
        IPv6 destination address of each packet. The high-order bits of the
        IPv6 destination address are used by intermediate routers for unicast
        forwarding, deciding whether a packet is a BIER packet, and if so, to
        identify the BIER Sub-Domain, Set Identifier and BitString length. No
        additional extension or encapsulation header is required. Instead of
        encapsulating the packet in IPv6, the payload is attached to the BIER
        IPv6 header and the IPv6 protocol number is set to the type of the
        payload. If the payload is UDP, the UDP checksum needs to change when
        the BitString in the IPv6 destination address changes.</t>

        <t/>
      </section>

      <section title="Add BIER header into IPv6 Extension Header ">
        <t><figure>
            <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
   +---------------+-----------------+-------------------
   |  IPv6 header  | IPv6 Ext header | payload
   |               | (BIER header in |
   |               |  TLV Type = X)  |
   | Next Header   |   Next Header   |
   +---------------+-----------------+-------------------
          ]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>

        <t>According to <xref target="RFC8200"/> In IPv6, optional
        internet-layer information is encoded in separate headers that may be
        placed between the IPv6 header and the upper- layer header in a
        packet. There is a small number of such extension headers, each one
        identified by a distinct Next Header value. An IPv6 packet may carry
        zero, one, or more extension headers, each identified by the Next
        Header field of the preceding header. Extension headers (except for
        the Hop-by-Hop Options header) are not processed, inserted, or deleted
        by any node along a packet's delivery path, until the packet reaches
        the node (or each of the set of nodes, in the case of multicast)
        identified in the Destination Address field of the IPv6 header. The
        Hop-by-Hop Options header is not inserted or deleted, but may be
        examined or processed by any node along a packet's delivery path,
        until the packet reaches the node (or each of the set of nodes, in the
        case of multicast) identified in the Destination Address field of the
        IPv6 header. The Hop-by-Hop Options header, when present, must
        immediately follow the IPv6 header. Its presence is indicated by the
        value zero in the Next Header field of the IPv6 header.</t>

        <t>Two of the currently-defined extension headers are the Hop-by-Hop
        Options header and the Destination Options header which carry a
        variable number of type-length-value (TLV) encoded "options".</t>

        <t/>

        <t>In <xref target="I-D.xie-bier-ipv6-encapsulation"/> an IPv6 BIER
        Destination Option is carried by the IPv6 Destination Option Header
        (indicated by a Next Header value 60). It is initialized in a packet
        sent by an IPv6 BFIR router to inform the following BFR routers in an
        IPv6 BIER domain to replicate to destination BFER routers hop-by-hop.
        BIER is generally a hop-by-hop and one-to-many architecture and it is
        required for a BIER IPv6 encapsulation to include the BIER Header
        ([RFC8296]) as an IPv6 Extension Header, to pilot the hop-by-hop BIER
        replication.</t>

        <t>Hop by hop Options Headers may be considered. The Hop-by-Hop
        Options header is used to carry optional information that may be
        examined and processed by every node along a packet's delivery path.
        The Hop-by-Hop Options header is identified by a Next Header value of
        0 in the IPv6 header.</t>

        <t>Defining New Extension Headers and Options may also be considered,
        if the IPv6 Destination Option Header is not good enough and new
        extension headers can solve the problem better.</t>

        <t>Such proposals may include requests to IANA to allocate a "BIER
        Option" code from "Destination Options and Hop-by-Hop Options", and/or
        a "BIER Option Header" code from "IPv6 Extension Header Types".</t>

        <t/>
      </section>

      <section title="Transport BIER as IPv6 payload">
        <t><figure>
            <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
   +---------------+-----------------+-------------------
   |  IPv6 header  | IPv6 Ext header | BIER Hdr + payload
   |               |    (optional)   | as IPv6 payload
   |               |                 |
   | Next Header   | Next Header = X |
   +---------------+-----------------+-------------------
          ]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>

        <t>There is a proposal for a transport-independent BIER encapsulation
        header which is applicable regardless of the underlying transport
        technology. As described in <xref target="I-D.xu-bier-encapsulation"/>
        and <xref target="I-D.zhang-bier-bierin6"/>, the BIER header, and the
        payload following it, can be combined as an IPv6 payload, and be
        indicated by a new Upper-layer IPv6 Next-Header value. A unicast IPv6
        destination address is used for the replication and changes when
        replicating a packet out to a neighbor.</t>

        <t>Such proposals may include a request to IANA to allocate an IPv6
        Next-Header code from "Assigned Internet Protocol Numbers".</t>

        <t/>
      </section>

      <section title="Tunnelling BIER in a IPv6 tunnel">
        <t><figure>
            <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
   +---------------+-----------------+------------+----------------
   |  IPv6 header  | IPv6 Ext header | GRE header |
   |               |    (optional)   |            | BIER Hdr + 
   |               |                 |            | payload as GRE 
   | Next Header   |   Next Header   | Proto = X  | Payload
   +---------------+-----------------+------------+----------------
          ]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>

        <t>A generic IPv6 Tunnel could be used to encapsulate the bier packet
        within an IPv6 domain.</t>

        <t>GRE is a mechanism by which any ethernet payload can be carried by
        an IP GRE tunnel due to the 16-bits 'Protocol Type' field. Both IPv4
        and IPv6 can be used to carry GRE. The Ethernet type codepoint 0xAB37,
        defined for BIER, can be used in a GRE header to indicate the
        subsequent BIER header and payload in an IPv6 network.</t>

        <t><figure>
            <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
   +---------------+-----------------+------------+----------------
   |  IPv6 header  | IPv6 Ext header | UDP header |
   |               |    (optional)   |            | BIER Hdr + 
   |               |                 |            | payload as UDP 
   | Next Header   |   Next Header   | DPort = X  | Payload
   +---------------+-----------------+------------+----------------
          ]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>

        <t>UDP-based tunnelling is another mechanism which uses a specific UDP
        port to indicate a UDP payload format. Both IPv4 and IPv6 can support
        UDP. Such UDP-based tunnels can be used for BIER in a IPv6 network by
        defining a new UDP port to indicate the BIER header and payload.</t>

        <t/>
      </section>
    </section>
    
    
  </back>
</rfc>
